Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[join team or mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Consort Fleur, what is the matter with you?
Why would you spoil the mood on such a joyous day?
I'm have no grievance over anything.
I lost my composure because I was overcome with
emotions watching Lady Sourire's performance.
You were not in the family yet when
Empress Première performed the dance.
Why would you feel emotional about the dance?
I came across Lament from the East Tower
by Consort Mei when I idled my days away in poetry.
I dreaded as I read her sentimental poem.
While she performed Dance of the Startled Swan
as a favorite consort of Emperor Xuanzong of Tang,
she wrote Lament from the East Tower
during her confinement in the Shangyang Palace.
The dance reminds me of this poem.
I can't stop feeling disconsolate for Consort Mei.
You've never had much interest in poetry.
How come you grew fond of it?
I learnt that poetry can enlighten a benighted mind.
Devoid of talent and virtue, I would have no face
to serve Your Majesty if I don't cultivate my character.
If you sympathize with the poem,
why not share your thoughts with us?
“Your fond words said
your love would bind us inseparably.”
"It’d endure the sun and the moon,"you vowed,
"it’d abide as mountains and seas."
“How she [Yang Guifei, another consort]
seethed in wrathful jealousy.”
“How she scolded me into
the forlorn tower away from my beloved."
“Nowhere can I reach the halcyon days of yore;
no more can I see than a haze in my dreams.”
Every time I read these lines, I am deeply saddened
by her love and longing for her husband.
Your Majesty, the matter concerning Consort Fleur
is a family affair in your palace,
which I dare not comment on.
It's just that Her Highness had not committed
any serious wrongs for all these past years.
If there was something unthoughtful in her service,
I hope Your Majesty would forgive Her Highness
on account of her many years of service.
Consort Fleur, it must have been hard on you.
Your residence is remote in the Summer Palace.
I'll visit you oftener when I have time.
I thank Your Majesty.
I'd like to ask you ...
The slip of paper was being kept in your sleeve, wasn't it?
How my dance was orchestrated to happen!
I shall thank you for the effort.
Sourire, what are you talking about?
I do not understand.
Your acute mind understands that without Dance of the
Startled Swan, there would not be Lament from the East Tower.
While the heart-rending poem by Consort Mei did not
re-capture the love of Emperor Xuanzong,
Her Highness Consort Fleur changed His Majesty's mind.
Consort Mei would very much appreciate your kind thought.
Whatever you say, Sourire.
My ineloquent tongue is unable to vindicate myself.
You might as well spend more time with Lady Vertu.
Her pregnancy is the prime concern of His Majesty after all.
By all means.
We spent all the effort to take her down,
only to have to watch her rise up again.
How frustrating!
Meizhuang, you know it, her rise is always expected.
It's just a matter of time.
I'm afraid that the bad days will come back on us again.
With this person, there's nothing we need to worry about.
Don't make yourself angry over anything.
This is our priority.
It is just one month old.
And we don't even know if it's a boy or a girl.
May it be a boy or girl,
it will always be our dearest love.
Dear baby, tell mother to stop being angry.
You stop.
The Empress must be feeling more frustrated than we are.
Let's not fret before she does.
You are right.
But I couldn't stop feeling worried when I saw you dance.
I knew that you can dance well, but I never expected
a dance to be of such difficult choices.
I got by with sheer luck.
But we can never be too careful about
Lady Cao's deep cunning and guile.
But His Majesty's fondness of you
will shield you from her plots.
It must be hard for you to conceal
your talents from His Majesty.
Had you exhibited your abilities earlier,
she wouldn't lay a trap for you over dancing.
It's fortunate that they are not aware of my talents.
Otherwise they would be brazenly plotting against me.
Lady Sourire, His Majesty wishes to share with you
the poems that he has newly collected.
Go immediately. Don't make His Majesty wait.
I'll see you later.
- Mr Su.
- Peace to Lady Sourire.
His Majesty is in a meeting with a few mandarins.
I hope you won't mind waiting here for a while, My Lady.
Certainly.
Your Majesty, considering the ongoing wars in the northwest,
the service of General Nian Gengyao
is critical for the country.
I hope Your Majesty will reconsider.
We should act in an expedient manner.
Your Majesty's forgiveness for Consort Fleur
will boost the morale of the soldiers.
I understand. You can leave now.
Peace to My Lady.
My Lady, please.
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire is here.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
I'm having a headache. I need a massage.
Yes.
There's something troubling Your Majesty.
How do you know?
Despite the jasmine flowers in the chamber,
I can still detect the smell of menthol.
I know Your Majesty applies menthol
when there's something bothering you.
You always understand me.
Take a guess at what is bothering me.
Your Majesty is concerned with everything under Heaven.
It must be something at court.
You are not wrong,
but the harem is under Heaven as well.
It is difficult for the Empress
to manage the harem single-handed.
It is time that someone share her burden.
What do you think?
Consort Fleur had always assisted
Her Majesty with the palace affairs.
Whatever happened was the mistake of Concubine Beauté.
Consort Fleur was not necessarily involved.
The Empress Dowager was simply
unsatisfied about Consort Fleur being arbitrary.
I believe she has learned her lesson.
That would make you feel aggrieved.
But don't worry, I'll protect you from any harm.
I would never feel aggrieved
to do anything for Your Majesty.
It was such a rare occurrence that State Prince Dun
would speak up for Your Highness.
He has always been a haughty man,
not even respectful to His Majesty.
He's entitled to be superior.
His mother, Noble Consort Wenxi,
is the younger sister of Empress Xiaozhaoren
while the current Empress Dowager was the
preceptor maid of Empress Xiaozhaoren.
After the battle for the throne among the nine lords,
although his associates
Lord VIII, Lord IV, and Lord XIV were banished,
he is still able to retain the title of "State Prince".
But he cannot swallow his anger
seeing His Majesty risen to the throne.
The why would he help Your Highness?
He's not helping me.
He is taking this opportunity
to earn a favor from my brother.
Great General Nian?
As a highly ranked prince, he was able to work with
my brother on affairs in Qinghai Province.
Perhaps he did it for old times' sake.
For whatever reason, I feel happy for Your Highness
as long as His Majesty is visiting.
Is the dress ready?
It is, Your Highness.
His Majesty likes to see Your Highness in red.
- Help me get dressed quickly.
- Yes, Your Highness.
I must not make His Majesty wait.
Your Majesty had a long day.
You should sleep early.
I made my face sore from all the smiling.
On such an occasion, Your Majesty has to
put on one smile after another.
It must be difficult for Your Majesty.
An empress must never say she's tired.
Those who covet my throne will eat me alive
if they ever catch me feeling fatigued.
Your Majesty is right.
How disgusting was the smug face of Consort Fleur!
(sigh) But that does not disgust His Majesty.
But I couldn't help thinking of Honghui,
my son, on his first birthday.
If the First Prince were still with us ...
If Honghui were with us,
he must be taller than the Third Prince,
and handsomer.
And much smarter than the Third Prince.
Indeed. Honghui began to read
when he was two years old.
The Third Prince has nothing to compare to him.
Your Majesty is in the prime of life.
Your will certainly have one more son.
I'm past forty years of age,
not eligible for pregnancy any more.
And after my sister died, His Majesty
never treated me as he used to.
I know the condition of my health.
I'm afraid I'll never be able to.
Although His Majesty doesn't say so,
he respects you very much in his heart.
Huh,
what is the use of respect
for a woman who is not loved by her husband?
You've been through all these years with me.
How do you think His Majesty
has treated me compared to my sister?
Your Majesty, before Empress Première entered
the family, His Majesty treated you extremely well.
His Majesty never loved me
as much as he loved my sister.
Same with the Empress Dowager.
After all, I am the daughter of a secondary wife
while she of the primary wife.
If only Honghui were with us,
he would be the eldest son and of a primary wife.
What a distinguished prince he would be!
When Honghui was dying,
it was raining just like this.
Autumn,
my head aches terribly.
Your Majesty ...
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
My Lady, how is your appetite lately?
Do you still feel nauseous?
This is strange.
I don't feel nauseous lately.
But my stomach aches and feels cold.
I wonder what the reason is.
My Lady, you will continue to feel at ease
as you have been taking the prenatal tonics.
As for stomach pain ...
it is normal one month in pregnancy.
Thank you for your reassurance.
I thought the pregnancy symptoms
would be strong by this time.
Nay. You are in good health, My Lady.
You would not have the symptoms.
I believe you will give birth to a prince for His Majesty.
Thank you for your auspicious words.
- Lunar.
- Yes.
Offer Dr Liu some of the hawthorn cakes my father sent.
Thank you, My Lady.
Aiya, the hawthorn cake must be
made by Qishunzhai Bakery.
Qishunzhai was closed the year before last.
Dr Liu, you were transferred to Beijing this year.
How come you didn't know?
Er ...
I would always think of the bakery when I miss home.
That is why I always felt like the store was still there.
I apologize for my slip of the tongue.
You must be missing home a lot.
I will let Lunar send you more if you like.
I thank My Lady in advance.
- Poria.
- Yes.
- Please see Doctor Liu out.
Please follow me, Doctor Liu.
Thank you, My Lady.
Please have a break, My Lady.
Don't strain your eyes.
This one is almost done.
I shall finish it.
What are you in a hurry for?
Lady Vertu is just one month in her pregnancy.
You will have eight more months to finish the bib.
I must finish this as soon as possible.
If Meizhuang likes it, I will make a few more.
You have no idea how fast a baby grows.
They outgrow the clothes in no time.
It's not like you've had children of your own.
When I was home, I watched my mother
doing needlework for the children of the concubines.
That was how I have the knowledge.
I'm sorry to have stirred up
your sad memories, My Lady.
I will take any punishment.
Please rise.
Why would I punish you?
I was just missing my mother.
I wonder how she has been.
She must be well esteemed
for you have entered the palace.
I'm just a neglected Companion.
His Majesty might not even remember me.
The dragon will have to stay where it is
before a chance to soar.
My Lady, I have bad news.
What happened?
Mr An had an accident.
My Lady.
Sourire.
Meizhuang, help me!
- Longrong, what happened?
- Rise. Take it easy.
My father is in jail!
How did that happen?
I received a letter from home
saying while my father was assisting Magistrate
Jiang Wenqing in a mission to transport the army provisions,
the enemy troops appeared halfway and snatched the provisions.
Jiang Wenqing escaped with part of the money.
His Majesty, out of trembling fury,
held captive Jiang Wenqing with my father.
I don't know if he will live or not.
I'm afraid His Majesty would
sentence my father to death in fierce anger.
Are you sure if your father wasn't involved at all?
I am sure!
My father has always been circumspect in his dealings.
He would never involve himself in something like this.
Don't cry, Lingrong.
There's no conclusion to this matter yet.
We need to think of a solution.
Exactly.
I understand that anything concerning
the military is of great consequence.
I'm afraid the odds are not in my father's favor.
We will definitely try to speak to His Majesty on your behalf.
It's just that ... we are not allowed to speak of the state affairs.
You're right.
There's no need to disturb His Majesty.
In fact, Meizhuang can help me.
Me?
It happened within the jurisdiction of Jizhou.
Your father, as the governor, will be the interrogator.
- Meizhuang, I beg of you to help my father.
- Please stand.
I will see what I can do.
I need to think ...
Please have mercy on my father.
A letter from you will suffice.
Of course, don't worry.
But I must see His Majesty first to sound him out.
Thank you, Meizhuang!
I'm eternally grateful for your help.
Lingrong, don't cry.
Aiyo, Lady Vertu ...
What brought you here carrying the child?
I hope you were not troubled by the heat.
Is His Majesty inside?
Yes, but he's with Zhang Tingyu and General Longkodo.
I'm afraid you'll have to wait for a while, My Lady.
How come General Longkodo is even here?
An accident happened to the
army provisions for the north west.
His Majesty is outraged about it.
Does that involve Companion An's father?
That I have no idea.
Er ... All I know is that His Majesty has announced
the head official, Jiang Wenqing to be beheaded.
What ... what about the other officials?
I don't know about that.
So ... you came here for Companion An's father, My Lady?
Yes, Companion An was overcome with grief.
I have to do something.
No no no ...
In my view, My Lady, all you can do is watch.
I hope you would enlighten me, sir.
His Majesty strongly disapproves interference of
the concubines in the state affairs.
This accident concerns
General Nian Gengyao in particular.
It is equivalent to opposition to
Consort Fleur if you speak for Companion An.
But this is not about opposing anyone.
I cannot just stand by and watch
when I can save someone's life.
I'm afraid that is what you will have to do.
If you would give it more thought,
whether His Majesty knows your involvement or not,
your father will be lenient once he receives your letter.
But if someone should make a fuss about
your involvement and provoke anger in His Majesty,
wouldn't that peril your father's career?
But what if Companion An's father is not guilty ...
If so, he will be proved innocent after investigation.
You didn't see how furious His Majesty was just now.
You must not risk your future for this matter.
And you are with child and in sight of
power to assist with palace management,
why would you wade into the muddy water?
And if Her Highness Consort Fleur
hears about your involvement,
Companion An's father will have to die.
I ...
(sigh)
- Please don't tell His Majesty I came.
- Yes.
It is very hot out here.
Please go quickly, My Lady.
Don't be sad.
We'll think of something else.
What else can we do?
Meizhuang wasn't even able to do anything about it.
No one else would be able to help me.
What Meizhuang said is within reason.
If she speaks up for you, Consort Fleur
will spare no effort to put your father to death.
But what can I do?
His Majesty has announced the
immediate execution of Jiang Wenqing today.
Tomorrow ... it could be my father.
Let's go see the Empress.
The Empress ...
Peace to My Ladies.
May I trouble you to inform Her Majesty
that Companion An and I wish to see her?
You've come at an unfortunate time, My Ladies.
Her Majesty is not here.
If I recall correctly, it should be the time
for Her Majesty to rise from her afternoon nap.
Her Majesty went to the Governance Hall.
My Ladies, I believe it was the same matter that
brought you here despite the summer heat.
Her Majesty is resourceful.
She expected our visit and went to see His Majesty first.
It is uncertain when Her Majesty will be back.
Would you mind waiting in the side chamber?
Tea has been prepared.
Thank you, Madam Autumn.
Please.
The Empress went to the governance Hall?
What for in the midday heat?
I learned that Her Majesty was pleading
the case of An Bihuai, Companion An's father.
You mean, the person who failed to escort the army provisions?
Your Highness's brother, General Nian,
is fighting valiantly on the frontier
while they couldn't do such
a small thing for him at the back end.
It's no wonder that his majesty is enraged.
Only ...
Is Your Highness going to make the trip
after the Empress did a favor for Companion An?
Isn't she very close to Lady Sourire and Lady Vertu?
They are like sisters.
Huh, no one can be like sisters in the harem.
It's just the weak being reliant on the strong,
and the unintelligent obedient to the wise.
Sisters of today will become tomorrow's nemeses.
A smile in the face hides a stab in the back.
Your Highness's words are sharp
as a needle that draws blood with one prick.
As for managing the harem,
would you prefer a velvet glove or an iron fist?
My dull-witted mind knows nothing like this.
Conflicts occur wherever the women are.
They cry with scheming tears,
and laugh with conflicting minds.
They are a pond of stillwater,
beneath which turbulent flows surge.
Were I to manage the harem,
I would rule with an iron fist and iron heart.
I dare them to ignore law and discipline
under severe punishment.
Your Highness is absolutely right.
Her Majesty the Empress arrives.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
All rise.
Have a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
I did all I could to help Companion An's father.
But it wasn't up to me.
His Majesty said nothing more than it was a matter in court.
If Your Majesty says so ...
That is all I can do as well.
For the time being, we can only wish the best for your father,
and see whether His Majesty will be open to negotiation.
Lingrong is most grateful to
Your Majesty's help and consideration.
I will always remember your benevolence.
You may rise.
Misfortune can happen to anyone.
(sigh) I am not only the head of harem,
but also a sister to you all in the family.
I must help you whenever I can.
No matter how things turn out,
we are eternally grateful for Your Majesty's words.
I feel disheartened by the sneering arrogance of
Consort Fleur ever since I entered the palace.
Your Majesty is a caring, motherly presence in the harem.
I ...
Lady Sourire, you are a sensible person.
You must offer comfort to Companion An.
I share the same gratitude as Companion An
for Your Majesty's caring support.
How may we possibly requite Your Majesty?
Amid one trouble after another in the harem, my health
condition doesn't allow me so much energy to deal with them.
With your perceptive mind, Lady Sourire,
you can spare me the worries if you know what they are.
Aiya,
on such a hot day, the ash in the censer is going to reflame.
What can we do about it?
It is by the grace of Your Majesty
that we can have a peaceful life in the palace.
It is hence our duty to share the burden of Your Majesty.
While the wise exhaust their mind, we humble concubines
will follow Your Majesty exerting our physical effort.
Very well, you did not let me down.
"Under the bright moon and faint stars,
fly the crows to the south afar."
"They encircle a tree for many a time,"
finally to be able to rest upon a branch.
[She changed a line in Duan Ge Xing by Cao Cao]
In sooth, there is only one tree in the harem
despite the bright-colored flowers to deceive your eyes.
As long as you can see the tree from the flowers.
I thank Your Majesty.
I will always remember your advice.
Consort Fleur is aware that the Empress
has seen His Majesty for An Bihuai.
There is no one more concerned about
Her Majesty than Consort Fleur at the moment.
Take a guess what Consort Fleur is doing right now.
Presumably, she is doing
the opposite of what Her Majesty did.
She is pleading with His Majesty to punish An Bihuai severely.
We must thank her if that's the case.
How so, My Lady?
We must thank her effort to save me some trouble.
When did you come in?
I wasn't even aware.
You were soundly asleep, Si Lang.
I wouldn't have the heart to disturb you.
The documents are never exhausted before I am.
I spent the entire day reading these before I know it.
Those old fogies write about anything they can to bother me.
It is their duty as the officials.
Si Lang need not be too tough on them.
And the work wasn't as exhausting while
the affectionate ladies came to keep you company.
It must have been a poetic scene
where a red cuff perfumes the book.
Hmm, it smells really good.
I've spoiled your sassy tongue.
Huan Huan is not as considerate
as Her Highness Consort Fleur.
All I do is to upset Si Lang.
How do you know Consort Fleur came here?
The fan is scented with the Celestial Palace,
a rarity in rouge that is exquisitely crafted.
Only few in the palace are able to use it.
While Her Majesty is not into perfume,
Her Highness must be elegantly dressed
when she came to see Your Majesty.
That is how the fan was scented with her rouge.
You do see the wind direction from a straw.
Si Lang, just tell me if I'm right.
Your eyes see everything.
Consort Fleur set her foot in when the Empress had just left.
They came here for the same person.
For Companion's father, An Bihuai?
Exactly.
What about you?
What brought you here?
Let me take a guess.
Her Majesty is a kind-hearted.
She must be pleading for Companion An.
Her Highness is high-minded.
She must be in favor of impersonal law enforcement.
What about you?
The harem must not interfere with the state affairs.
Huan Huan has always remembered it.
Since Her Majesty and Her Highness
had opposing views on the same issue,
I'm curious whether the case is worth further examination.
What do you mean?
From my reading of history, the illustrious emperors
tended to punish the heads while show mercy to the dependents.
This would inspire not only reverence
but also gratitude in the people.
As an admirer of the founding emperors
of the Tang and Song Dynasties,
Your Majesty is a sagacious and benevolent emperor as well.
In my humble opinion,
the reign is bright when outward wars
and inward penalties are clear.
I only knew you are well-read in literature,
but you are also proficient in history and politics.
You inform governance in light of history
without direct reference to the state affairs.
I'm grateful to have you as the jewel in my crown.
I will have An Bihuai's case re-investigated.
No innocent should be unfairly imprisoned.
I hope Your Majesty would pardon
my brazen violation of the rules as a woman.
While the harem cannot interfere in the court,
you are my wife when you are alone with me.
From history to politics, you can speak
freely of anything with your husband.
There's nothing wrong with that.
I dare not.
Lady Sourire doesn't dare to, but Zhen Huan does.
I dare not overstep my bounds before Your Majesty,
but Huan Huan will talk her heart out to Si Lang.
Congratulations, My Lady!
Thank you, Madam...
What happened?
By His Majesty's order, Shen Zishan, the Governor
of Jizhou will re-investigate the case for your father.
We are hopeful that he will be released.
Really?
Of course.
As the Empress pleaded for the case,
His Majesty must give her face.
I thank Her Majesty.
Not now, My Lady. You should thank Her Majesty
in person when your father is all right.
It seems that Lady Sourire went to see His Majesty as well.
Lady Vertu and Lady Sourire are like sisters to you, My Lady!
Sourire treats me wholeheartedly
while Meizhuang ...
Lady Vertu has sent a letter to Mr Shen
to take care of the case.
Anyone can give a push to the boat
when it's carried by the current.
In fact, His Majesty would surely
pardon Mr An as the Empress spoke for you.
If only Lady Vertu had sent the letter earlier,
you wouldn't have to worry so much, My Lady.
I have errands to run.
Please allow me to leave, My Lady.
Take care, Madam.
Cuckoo ...
Collect some valuable jewelry of mine.
My family must have spent a lot of money to buy some favors.
My mother must be having a hard time
at home if I don't help her.
She suffers from poor eyesight.
My father's concubines bully her.
Were if not for my aunt's help,
I couldn't imagine how hard her life would be.
It's good that you received
plenty of jewelry from Lady Sourire.
What is the use of even the finest jewelry?
I finally learned that no one else
is more helpful than the Empress.
Of course, the Empress is the most important woman
in the palace excluding the Empress Dowager.
Now I know I can never depend on anyone else.
Meizhuang addresses me as her sister,
but avoids me like a plague in a crisis.
My Lady, I feel that Lady Sourire is sincere to you.
I know in my heart who is good to me.
My Lady, I think you should rely on
yourself rather than anyone else.
You can make your parents proud of you
by gaining favor for yourself.
I'm incapable of that, and devoid of a chance to do so.
As long as you have the will to do it, My Lady.
Why are you not fanning My Lady inside?
She is with His Majesty.
I have to chase away the cicadas
for My Lady to have a good nap.
What's the use of clearing the cicadas on this tree?
There are so many trees in the outer yard.
Hey, you should do it with me!
My Lady sent me to collect some lotus flowers
before she finishes her nap.
I need to put them into a vase.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
I didn't know Your Majesty is here.
Ma Lady, I didn't meant to disturb you.
It was an honest mistake.
You must be Jade, who always wears jade.
Yes, Your Majesty has a good memory.
You may leave after you put away the flowers.
Yes.
Why did you put the flowers in a bowl?
Your Majesty, I was hoping to keep them floating
in the bowl the way they're blooming on the lake.
You have a pretty face and yet a more beautiful mind.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Even your maid is like you.
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.